<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references.
-->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
      please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->


<rfc category="info" docName="draft-mink-5g-ns-transport-ps-00">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-mink-5g-ns-transport-ps-00">
      Analysis and Problem Statements for Interworking between 5G Network Slicing and Transport Network
    </title>

    <author fullname="Takuya Miyasaka" initials="T." surname="Miyasaka">
      <organization>KDDI Research</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2-1-15, Ohara, Fujimino-shi</street>
          <city>Saitama</city>
          <region/>
          <code>356-8502</code>
          <country>JP</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ta-miyasaka@kddi-research.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kenji Kumaki" initials="K." surname="Kumaki">
      <organization>KDDI</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3-22-7, Yoyogi, Shibuya-ku</street>
          <city>Tokyo</city>
          <region/>
          <code>151-0053</code>
          <country>JP</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ke-kumaki@kddi.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tomonobu Niwa" initials="T." surname="Niwa">
      <organization>KDDI</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3-22-7, Yoyogi, Shibuya-ku</street>
          <city>Tokyo</city>
          <region/>
          <code>151-0053</code>
          <country>JP</country>
        </postal>
        <email>to-niwa@kddi.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date day="26" month="June" year="2018"/>

    <area></area>

    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document describes problem statements for realizing an end-to-end network slicing that is expected to provide service-oriented communications between users and applications.
        3GPP introduced the network slicing concept in 5G architecture (3GPP Release 15), however, it mainly focuses on mobile access and core domains.
        In order to reap the benefit of the concept, a network slicing needs to be designed across multiple domains of the network including non-3GPP parts.
        This document analyzes current 3GPP 5G network slicing architecture and summarizes problem statements for interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        An End-to-End(E2E) network slicing is expected to cater to much greater diversity of requirements for wide variety of services such as V2X services and factory automation.
        Here, the E2E means that a network slicing penetrates all network domains: mobile networks, transport networks and so forth.
        Network operators anticipate that it is possible to tailor the network to fit for service-oriented demands in a timely and cost-effective way, which in turn reduces OPEX and CAPEX.
      </t>
      <t>
        3GPP is leading a network slicing concept in 5G system (3GPP Release 15).
        3GPP network slicing is defined as a logical network that provides specific network capabilities and network characteristics.
        However, it covers a limited domains and mainly focuses on an isolation for 5G network functions.
        In order to achieve the goal, the network slicing needs to be designed from the E2E perspectives, not only 3GPP but also non-3GPP including transport networks.
      </t>
      <t>
        The way to map transport networks to 5G system for network slicing can be classified into two parts: inside and outside 5G system.
        Inside 5G system, network connections between UE, RAN, UPF and DN can be identified as network slice with one or more QoS Flow rules, and thus its underlying transport network should also be aware of the network slice.
        Outside 5G system, the E2E network slicing shall concatenate the network slicing whthin 5G systems with that of the following transport networks.
        To this end, a method to stitch user plane traffic to/from UPF and logical tunnels in transport networks (e.g. MPLS-TE) is required.
      </t>
      <t>
        Therefore, in terms of the E2E network slicing, the transport network shall accommodate to 5G system.
        This document analyzes current 5G network slicing architecture and summarizes problem statements for interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network.
      </t>
      <section title="Scope of this document">
        <t>
          The scope of this document is to analyze interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network and summarize problem statements for the interworking.
          <xref target="fig_int_ns_te" /> shows an E2E communication between UE and CP(Content Provider Server) on 5G network slicing environment.
          We define each term used in the scope with <xref target="fig_int_ns_te" /> as follows.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig_int_ns_te" title="E2E communication between UE and CP">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
      + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
      | Network Slice Instance(NS1)         |
+--+    +---+          +---+          +---+
|UE+--|-+RAN|          |UPF|----------|DN | |
+--+    +-|-+          +-|-+          +-|-+
      + - + - - - - - - -+- - - - - - - + - +
          |              |              |
    + - - + - - - - - - -|- - +   + - - + - - - - - - - - - +
    |     |              |    |   |     |                   |
          |    +----+    |              |    +----+
    |     |    | R2 |    |    |   |     |    | R6 |         |
          |    +----+    |              |    +----+
    |     |   /     \    |    |   |     |   /     \         |
       +--|-+/       \+--|-+         +--|-+/       \+----+     +--+
    |  | R1 |         | R4 |  |   |  | R5 |         | R8 |--+--|CP|
       +--|-+\       /+--|-+         +--|-+\       /+----+     +--+
    |     |   \     /    |    |   |     |   \     /         |
          |    +----+    |              |    +----+
    |     |    | R3 |    |    |   |     |    | R7 |         |
          |    +----+    |              |    +----+
    |     | Transport    |    |   |     | Transport         |
          | Network      |              | Network
    |     | Inside 5GC   |    |   |     | Outside 5GC       |
    + - - + - - - - - - -|- - +   + - - + - - - - - - - - - +
          |              |              |
      + - + - - - - - - -+- - - - - - - + - +
+--+    +-|-+          +-|-+          +-|-+
|UE+--|-+RAN|          |UPF|----------|DN | |
+--+    +---+          +---+          +---+
      | Network Slice Instance(NS2)         |
      + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Network slice instance
            </t>
          </list>
          Network slice instance is defined as "A set of Network Function instances and the required resources (e.g. compute, storage and networking resources) which form a deployed Network Slice" in <xref target="TS.23.501-3GPP" />.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Transport network
            </t>
          </list>
          The definition of transport network in this document is a network which provides network connectivity to 5G network functions such as UPF.
          The scope of transport network in this document is limited to layer-3 network, thus IPv4 and IPv6. This is because 3GPP adopted IPv4/IPv6 as a transport network of 5G user plane.
        </t>
        <t>
          There are two different transport networks in <xref target="fig_int_ns_te" />:
          the transport network inside 5G core network consists of R1, R2, R3, and R4
          and the transport network outside 5G core network consists of R5, R6, R7, and R8.
          Both inside and outside networks are within the scope of this document.
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Traffic engineering
            </t>
          </list>
          The definition of traffic engineering in this document is to control the traffic path of IPv4/IPv6 packet
          in order to fulfill each network slice instance's requirements. (e.g. bandwidth and latency)
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, there are two network slice instance in <xref target="fig_int_ns_te" />: NS1 and NS2.
          Suppose NS1 provides latency sensitive service such as V2X (in this case, UE is an automotive vehicle and CP is a control/monitoring server operated by a car vendor), an operator needs to perform traffic engineering in transport network to select a path that total latency between UE and CP is minimum.
          If one-way latency is measured as follows,
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>R1->R2->R4 : 1msec</t>
            <t>R1->R3->R4 : 2msec</t>
            <t>R5->R6->R8 : 9msec</t>
            <t>R5->R7->R8 : 6msec</t>
          </list>
          the traffic path of NS1 in transport network inside 5G core network is R1->R2->R4 and the traffic path of NS1 in transport network outside 5G core network is R5->R7->R8.
          Therefore, the E2E communication from UE to CP is "UE->RAN->R1->R2->R4->UPF->DN->R5->R7->R8->CP".
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Interworking
            </t>
          </list>
          The definition of interworking in this document is that network slice instance and transport network collaborate in order to perform the traffic engineering which fulfills requirements of network slice instance.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="5G Network Slicing and Transport Network">
      <section title="5G Network Slicing">
        <t>
          The 5G system architecture introduced the following key features:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              Separate the user plane (UP) functions from the control plane (CP) functions, allowing independent scalability and flexible deployments.
            </t>
            <t>
              Modularize the network function to enable flexible and efficient network slicing.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Thanks to the features, the deployed network slicing is comprised of a network slice instance that indicates set of network functions(e.g. UPF) and the required resources.
          S-NSSAI(Single Network Slice Selection Assistance Information) is used to identify a network slice and assists the selection of a particular network slice instance corresponding to the slice.
          A network slice instance can be associated with one or more S-NSSAIs, and an S-NSSAI can be associated with one or more network slice instances.
          NSI ID(Network Slice Instance Identifier) may identify a network slice instance corresponding to certain S-NSSAI.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Transport Network for End-to-End 5G Communication">
        <t>
          An E2E network slicing needs a cross-domain technology that covers 3GPP, transport networks and others (e.g. optical networks, data center networks).
          For the 5G system, the transport networks are classifled two parts; inside and outside 5G system.
        </t>
        <section title="Transport Network inside 5G System">
          <t>
            A PDU session belongs to one and only one specific network slice instance in 5G system.
            5G QoS model is based on QoS Flows that is the finest granularity of QoS differentiation in the PDU session.
            QoS Flow is characterised by QoS profile for RAN, QoS rules for UE and PDR(Packet Detection Rule) for UPF.
            DSCP can be optinally utilized to support QoS Flow, however, the QoS Flow does not correspond to the network slice one by one.
            Therefore, a network slice can not be identified from the persipective of transport networks.
            Regarding transport connectivity between different 3GPP nodes in network slice instance, transport networks shall take 3GPP link requirements (e.g. NSI ID, topology, QoS parameters, etc.) from the network slice into account.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Transport Network outside 5G System">
          <t>
            The S-NSSAI instructs which a PDU session is associated with a DN and a network slice instance.
            In the current 3GPP specification, transport networks cannot recognize S-NSSAI or NSI ID from UP directly and thus cannot map network slicing in 3GPP system to that of transport networks.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Management and Orchestration of 5G Network Slicing" anchor="sec_manage_system">
          <t>
            The management and orchestration of 5G network slicing is studied in 3GPP SA5.
            This study includes creation, modification, and elimination of network slice instance from 3GPP management system.
          </t>
          <t>
            In this 3GPP management system, the coordination with management system of non-3GPP parts also has been taken into account and
            transport network management is included in the scope of the management system.
            <xref target="fig_coordination_tn" /> shows a concept of 3GPP management system and coordination with transport network management system, which is described in section 4.7 of <xref target="TS.28.530-3GPP" />
            However, detailed analysis for the coordination with a transport network management system is not studied.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="fig_coordination_tn" title="E2E communication between UE and CP">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

                  +------------------------+
                  | 3GPP Management System |
                  +------------------------+
                             /|\
                              |
                              |
                             \|/
                    +-------------------+
                    | Transport Network |
                    | Management System |
                    +-------------------+
                      /|\    /|\    /|\
                       |      |      |
            +----------+      |      +------------+
            |                 |                   |
           \|/               \|/                 \|/
+---+     ----     +---+     ----     +---+     ----     +----------+
|RAN|----( TN )----|UPF|----( TN )----|DN |----( TN )----|App Server|
+---+     ----     +---+     ----     +---+     ----     +----------+

                                             * TN = Transport Network
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="General Procedure for Interworking between 5G Network Slicing and Transport Network" anchor="sec_procedure">
      <t>
        <xref target="fig_NS_interwork_arch" /> illustrates a general procedure for an interworking between 5G Network Slicing and Transport Network Traffic Engineering and
        we use following terminology in this figure.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            5G User Plane Function : A function which is related to 5G user plane. RAN, UPF, and DN are current 5G User Plane Fucntion defined by 3GPP.
          </t>
          <t>
            NS Forwarding Policy DB : A database which maintains a forwarding policy which needs to be applied to each NS instance.
          </t>
          <t>
            TE Indicator : An indicator which instructs an adequate forwarding policy to router for the NS instance and encoded in an incoming packet. MPLS label and SRv6 SRH are an example for TE indicator.
          </t>
          <t>
            5G IP Packet : An IPv4/IPv6 packet sents from 5G network function.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        The 5G network function performs the following procedures for an interworking.
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Recognize the NSI ID of an outgoing packet at 5G User Plane Function
          </t>
          <t>
            Decide an adequate forwarding policy which is performed on this network slice instance by inquiring to the NS Forwarding Policy DB.
          </t>
          <t>
            Encapsulate an outgoing 5G IP Packet with an adequate TE indicator for the forwarding policy of a network slice instance
          </t>
          <t>
            Send the encapsulated packet to the transport network
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_NS_interwork_arch" title="Interworking Procedure">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 5G Network Function
+-----------------+
|+---------------+|
|| NS Forwarding ||
|| Policy DB     ||
|+---------------+|
|   /|\    |      |
|    |     |      |
|    |     |      |
|    |    \|/     |
| +-------------+ |
| |5G User Plane| |
| |  Function   | | +------------+                  +------------+
| +-------------+ | |TE Indicator|                  |TE Indicator|
|       |         | +------------+      Router      +------------+
|      \|/        | |5G IP Packet| +--------------+ |5G IP Packet|
|  +----------+   | +------------+ | +----------+ | +------------+
|  |Data Plane|---+----------------+>|Data Plane|-|-------------->
|  +----------+   |                | +----------+ |    Next Router
+-----------------+                +--------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        <xref target="fig_NS_interwork_arch_example" /> shows an example of interworking procedure.
        In this example, the 5G network function uses MPLS-TE for traffic engineering in transport network and encapsulated with MPLS label which represents an adequate MPLS-TE tunnel which fulfills requirements of a network slice instance.
        The following list describes the detailed procedure in this example.
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            5G Network Function recognizes that the NSI ID of the outgoing packet is 123
          </t>
          <t>
            5G Network Function resolves the required traffic engineering policy is the MPLS-TE tunnel 123 for the network slice instance
          </t>
          <t>
            5G Network Function encapsulated the outgoing 5G IP packet with MPLS label of 123 which is the outgoing label of the MPLS-TE tunnel 123
          </t>
          <t>
            5G Network Function sends the encapsulated packet to the transport network
          </t>
        </list>

      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_NS_interwork_arch_example" title="Example of Interworking Procedure">
      <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 5G Network Function
+-------------------+
|+-----------------+|
|| NS Forwarding   ||
|| Policy DB       ||
||                 ||
||NSI ID:Policy    ||
||   111:MPLS-TE   ||
||       tunnel 111||
||       (HighBW)  ||
||   123:MPLS-TE   ||
||       tunnel 123||
||     (LowLatency)||
|+-----------------+|
|   /|\    |        |
|    |     |        |
|    |     |        |
| +-------------+   | +------------+                  +------------+
| |5G User Plane|   | | MPLS label |                  | MPLS label |
| |  Function   |   | |    123     |                  |    234     |
| +-------------+   | |(tunnel 123)|                  |(tunnel 123)|
|       |           | +------------+      Router      +------------+
|      \|/          | |5G IP Packet| +--------------+ |5G IP Packet|
|  +----------+     | +------------+ | +----------+ | +------------+
|  |Data Plane|-----+----------------+>|Data Plane|-|-------------->
|  +----------+     |                | +----------+ |    Next Router
+-------------------+                +--------------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section title="Analysis on Interworking">
      <t>
        This section describes an analysis on an interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network both outside 5G core network and inside 5G core network.
      </t>
      <section title="Analysis Assumption" anchor="sec_analysis_assumption">
        <t>
          <xref target="fig_assumption_5g" /> and the following list illustrates an assumption on 5G network slicing for our analysis.
          Sharing of network function (UPF and DN) among different network slice instances is suggested in section 4.5 of <xref target="TS.28.530-3GPP" />.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              UE can connect to the multiple network slice instances.
            </t>
            <t>
              RAN is a common network function to select adequate network slice instance's UPF.
            </t>
            <t>
              UPF may be shared between different network slice instances.
              The shared UPF has a common IP address/prefix for an endpoint.
            </t>
            <t>
              DN may be shared between different network slice instances.
              The shared DN has a common IP address/prefix for an endpoint.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <figure anchor="fig_assumption_5g" title="Analysis Assumption">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
                | NS1                             |
                    +-----+     +-----+     +---+
          +-----|---| UPF |-----| UPF |-----|   |-|
          |         +-----+     +-----+     |   |
          |     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - |DN | +
          |     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - |   | +
          |     | NS2                       |   | |
+--+    +-+-+                   +-----+     |   |
|UE+----+RAN+---|---------------|     |-----|   |-|
+--+    +-+-+                   |     |     +---+
          |     + - - - - - - - |     | - - - - - +
          |     + - - - - - - - | UPF | - - - - - +
          |     | NS3           |     |           |
          |         +-----+     |     |     +---+
          +-----|---| UPF |-----|     |-----|DN |-|
                    +-----+     +-----+     +---+
                + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Analysis inside 5G Core Network">
          <t>
            This section describes an analysis on an interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network inside 5G core network based on the procedure described in <xref target="sec_procedure" />.
            Problem statement in this analysis is emphasized as [PS-Interwork-X].
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="format [PS-Interwork-%d]:" counter="ps-interwork">
              <t>
                5G Network Function cannot recognize the NSI ID of an established PDU session. Therefore, statically configured Policy Based Routing(PBR) based traffic engineering is required.
              </t>
            </list>
            5G Network Function cannot recognize the NSI ID of an established PDU session due to the following two reasons.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                From user plane perspective, the NSI ID is not encoded in any header including GTP-U extension header.
                New PDU Session Container GTP-U extension header is introduced for 5G user plane in <xref target="TS.29.281-3GPP" />, but the extension header only includes QFI information.
              </t>
              <t>
                From control plane perspective, the NSI ID is not signaled to the user plane function such as UPF.
                PFCP is extended for 5G control plane protocol in <xref target="TS.29.244-3GPP" />, however, the NSI ID is not signaled to the user plane function.
              </t>
            </list>
            For this problem statement, we have to statically configure policy based routing(PBR) based traffic engineering in 5G network function.
            In <xref target="fig_example_pbr" />, an example for statically configured PBR in UPFb and UPFd is described in <xref target="fig_example_pbr_rib" />.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="fig_example_pbr" title="Example for PBR based traffic engineering">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
                | NS1 (NSI ID=1)                        |
                      +------+     +------+     +-----+
          +-----|-----| UPFa |-----| UPFb |-----| DNa | |
          |           +------+     +------+     +-----+
          |     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
          |     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
          |     | NS2 (NSI ID=2)                        |
+--+    +-+-+         +------+     +------+     +-----+
|UE+----+RAN+---|-----|      |-----|      |-----| DNb | |
+--+    +---+         |      |     |      |     +-----+
          |     + - - |      |- - -|      | - - - - - - +
          |     + - - | UPFc |- - -| UPFd | - - - - - - +
          |     |     |      |     |      |             |
          |           |      |     |      |     +-----+
          +-----|-----|      |-----|      |-----| DNc | |
                      +------+     +------+     +-----+
                | NS3 (NSI ID=3)                        |
                + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            In case of UPFd in <xref target="fig_example_pbr" />, statically configured PBR needs to include a source IP address classification
            because a destination IP address of next UPF (UPFc) is common as UPFc is shared between NS2 and NS3 as described in <xref target="sec_analysis_assumption" />.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="fig_example_pbr_rib" title="PBR based traffic engineering">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

   +------------------------------------------------------------+
   | Routing Table for UPFb                                     |
   | - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -|
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of UPFa>     |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 1> (for NS1)              |
   |                                                            |
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of DNa>      |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 2> (for NS2)              |
   +------------------------------------------------------------+

   +------------------------------------------------------------+
   |Routing Table for UPFd                                      |
   | - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -|
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of UPFc>     |
   |     AND Previous Node IP address is <IP address of DNb>    |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 1> (for NS2)              |
   |                                                            |
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of DNb>      |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 2> (for NS2)              |
   |                                                            |
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of UPFc>     |
   |     AND Previous Node IP address is <IP address of DNc>    |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 3> (for NS3)              |
   |                                                            |
   | IF: Subsequent Node IP address is <IP address of DNc>      |
   | THEN: Nexthop is <MPLS-TE tunnel 4> (for NS3)              |
   +------------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>
            <list style="format [PS-Interwork-%d]:" counter="ps-interwork">
              <t>
                5G network function cannot classify a network slice instance by using PBR If both previous node and subsequent node are shared between different network slice instances.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, a routing table for UPFc in <xref target="fig_example_pbr" /> toward RAN node cannot classify NS2 and NS3,
            because previous node is UPFb which is shared NS2 and NS3 and the subsequent node is RAN which is a common network function among network slice instances as described in <xref target="sec_analysis_assumption"/>.
            Therefore, the source IP address and the destination IP address are common among NS2 and NS3, so we cannot create an adequate PBR rule for each network slice instance.
          </t>
        </section>
      <section title="Interworking Analysis outside 5G Core Network">
        <t>
          TBD
        </t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Problem Statement Summary">
      <t>
        The following list summarizes problem statement for the interworking inside 5G core network.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="format [PS-Interwork-%d]:" counter="ps-interwork2">
          <t>
            5G Network Function cannot recognize the NSI ID of the established PDU session. Therefore, statically configured Policy Based Routing(PBR) based traffic engineering is required
          </t>
        </list>
        <list style="format [PS-Interwork-%d]:" counter="ps-interwork2">
          <t>
            5G network function cannot classify the network slice instance by using PBR If both previous node and subsequent node are shared between different network slice instances.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        The following list summarizes problem statement for the interworking outside 5G core network.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="format [PS-Interwork-%d]:" counter="ps-interwork2">
          <t>
            TBD
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conclusion">
      <t>
        This document summarizes problem statements for interworking between 5G network slicing and transport network.
        Our analysis shows the traffic engineering for 5G network slicing is achieved by using policy based routing.
        However, if 5G network function, e.g., UPF, is shared among different network slice instance,
        there is a case that the traffic engineering is not achieved because the 5G network function cannot distinguish network slice instance [PS-Interwork-2].
        This issue is inevitable under current 5G specification and we need to give the feedback to 3GPP to solve the issue.
      </t>
      <t>
        From IETF point of view, "transport network management system" is required from 3GPP SA5 WG as described in <xref target="sec_manage_system"/>.
        This transport network management system needs to serve a transport network related request sent from 3GPP management system,
        this means the transport network management system needs to provide API to 3GPP management system to control transport network from 3GPP side.
        Therefore IETF needs to collaborate with 3GPP, especially for 3GPP SA5 WG, and
        examine if current standardized technology and framework in IETF activity fulfill requirements from 3GPP.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Consideration">
    <t>TBD</t>
    </section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document does not require any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
    <t>
    The author would like to thank XXX for reviewing various iterations of
    the document and for providing content into various sections.
    </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!-- ***** BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

<!--
    <references title="Normative References">

    &RFC2119;

    </references>
-->
    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor='TR.29.891-3GPP' target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2017-12/Rel-15/29_series/29891-f00.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TR 29.891 (V15.0.0): 5G System Phase 1, CT WG4 Aspects</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2017"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.29.244-3GPP' target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/29_series/29244-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 29.244 (V15.1.0): Interface between the Control Plane and the User Plane Nodes; Stage 3</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.29.281-3GPP' target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/29_series/29281-f20.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 29.281 (V15.2.0): GPRS Tunneling Protocol User Plane (GTPv1-U)</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.23.501-3GPP' target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/23_series/23501-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 23.501 (V15.1.0): System Architecture for 5G System; Stage 2</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.23.502-3GPP' target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/23_series/23502-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 23.502 (V15.1.0): Procedures for 5G System; Stage 2</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.23.503-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/23_series/23503-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 23.503 (V15.1.0): Policy and Charging Control System for 5G Framework; Stage 2</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.38.300-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/38_series/38300-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 38.300 (v15.1.0): NR and NG-RAN Overall Description; Stage 2</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.38.401-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/38_series/38401-f10.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 38.401 (v15.1.0): NG-RAN; Architecture Description</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.38.415-3GPP'  target="http://ftp.3gpp.org//Specs/archive/38_series/38.415/38415-100.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 38.415 (v1.0.0): NG-RAN; PDU Session User Plane protocol (work in progress)</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.22.261-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-03/Rel-15/22_series/22261-f40.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 22.261 (V15.4.0): Service requirements for 5G system stage 1</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="March" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

       <reference anchor='TS.28.530-3GPP'  target="http://ftp.3gpp.org//Specs/archive/28_series/28.530/28530-100.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 28.530 (V1.0.0): Telecommunication management; Management and orchestration of networks and network slicing; Concepts, use cases and requirements</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

       <reference anchor='TS.29.561-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/FTP/Specs/2018-06/Rel-15/29_series/29561-f00.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 29.561 (V15.0.0): 5G System; Interworking between 5G Network and external Data Networks; Stage 3</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>


  </back>

</rfc>
